<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, February the 12th, 1692/3 by W. Fleetwood ...</title>
            <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39743</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12409088</idno>
  <idno type="VID">61463</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240969416</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R95</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12409088</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61463)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 276:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, February the 12th, 1692/3 by W. Fleetwood ...</title>
                  <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Newborough ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by Her Majesty's special command"</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Clergy --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61463:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61463:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN, AT <hi>WHITE-HALL, FEBRƲARY</hi> the 12<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> 1692/3.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. FLEETWOOD,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to their MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by her Majesty's Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Newborough,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:61463:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61463:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EZEKIEL xxxiij. 31.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>And they come unto thee as the People cometh, and they sit before thee as my People, and they hear thy Words, but they will not do them: For with their Mouth they shew much Love, but their heart goeth after their Covetousness.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THese Words are part of God's Complaint to and by the Prophet, of the People's Non-Proficiency under the Ministry of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and the other Messengers of God's Word; notwithstanding all the Shew and fair Appearance that they made, notwithstanding all the Forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness they came with to the House of God, the attentive Diligence they sat with, and the Love and Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing they pretended to the Sermons of the Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The Description of this is very plainly laid down in the Text, and it shall be my First Business, to consider it as plainly, and my Second to assign some Reasons as well as I can, Why both the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61463:3"/> heretofore and now our Ministry, is so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edifying and ineffectual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Son of Man</hi> (saith God to the Prophet, in the Verse before the Text) <hi>the Children of thy People still are talking against thee, by the Walls and in the Doors of the Houses:</hi> by talking <hi>against the Prophet</hi> is here meant <hi>about the Prophet,</hi> for it appears both from this, and the following Verses, That they liked the Prophet mightily; but because they acted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Instructions, they are said to talk <hi>against him,</hi> though in Words they talked in his Commendation: <hi>And speak one to another, every One to his Brother, saying, Come, I pray you, and hear what is the Word that cometh forth from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There could not, one would think, be a better Disposition in the World than this; they were not only careful and ready to hear the Word them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but zealous also of their Neighbour's good. They invited each his Brother with great tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, <hi>Come, I pray you, and hear, what is the Word that cometh forth from the Lord.</hi> Such a good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness was very pleasing heretofore to <hi>David, I was glad</hi> (said he <hi>Ps. 122. 1.) when they said unto me, Let us go into the House of the Lord.</hi> But it ended not in Invitations, for they came accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They come,</hi> (saith the Text) <hi>as the People cometh, i. e.</hi> in great Bands and Companies; they resort to the House of God in such Multitudes, that it looks
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61463:3"/> like the going forth of a Nation to sight, or the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together of a People to some mighty Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: to speak in the modern Phrase, the Place was throng'd exceedingly where-ever this <hi>Ezekiel</hi> preached or prophesied. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly, They sit before thee,</hi> saith God, <hi>as my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> They come and sit as People that profess to belong to God peculiarly; as People that would be signalized and known by their Relation to him, as distinguish'd from the whole World. They sit as gravely and demurely in the House of God, they listen and attend as heedfully, as is imaginable, so that you could not chuse but take them for God's People. There's all the external tokens and the gestures of Attention and Devotion possible to be shown; and there's no Man but would think they met to good Purpose. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly, They hear thy Words;</hi> they did not make this Noise and Invitation of each other, and resort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the House of God themselves in such great Companies, for nothing but to gaze about, or sleep, or talk impertinently, or worse, but to <hi>hear</hi> the Prophet, and they heard him. They came with full design and purpose to hear what was the Word that came forth from the Lord; that was their Errand and Intention, to be instructed in the Will of God, to know his Precepts and Commands from the Mouth of his Messenger and Prophet, and that they heard.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61463:4"/>
            <p>But <hi>Lastly,</hi> they did not only hear, but like, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and love the Word of God: <hi>With their Mouth they shew much Love. And lo</hi> (saith the Verse following the Text) <hi>thou art unto them as a very lovely Song, of one that hath a pleasant Voice, and can play well on an Instrument:</hi> They did not only like the Song it seems, but the way of singing it, the Grace and Air with which he set it off; they did not only approve the <hi>Matter</hi> of the Prophet's Sermon, but the Manner of its delivery too; the comely mien with which he spoke, his graceful way of Elocution, and the harmonious Cadence of his Voice. He had all the external Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well as internal, that a Man could want and wish for, and the People took great Notice of it, and had him in Esteem accordingly. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all these advantageous Ornaments in the Prophet, and all this Forwardness to hear, and favourable Disposition in the People towards him, yet it happened to his Serm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, as it does to lovely Songs, they pleased the Ear and struck the Fancy for the present, but made no deep and sensible Impression on the Mind and Understanding; they did not influence them to practise any whit, what they so long'd to hear, and liked when heard and uttered by him; for so it follows in the Text: <hi>They hear thy Words, but they will not do them. With their Mouth they shew much Love, but their Heart goeth</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61463:4"/>
               <hi>after their Covetousness. This People</hi> (as is elsewhere said) <hi>honoureth me with their Lips, but their Heart is far from me.</hi> Which is the second thing I am to speak to, and if I can, assign some Reasons how the Prophet's Sermons heretofore, and now our Ministry is so unedifying and ineffectual: And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> One Reason of some People's Non-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, may be this very Curiosity here described, this Itch of hearing One that preach'd so softly and so sweetly, and with so good a Grace, <hi>That his Words were to them as a very lovely Song, of one that hath a pleasant Voice.</hi> They came to hear the Word of the Lord because it sounded sweetly from his Mouth: Because his Voice was tuneable; his Gestures and Deportment manly, comely and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling; his Periods round and flowing, and his Elocution sweet and powerful. And when Men only come to take in <hi>Sound,</hi> they will unavoidably return <hi>empty:</hi> When they only hunt for <hi>Words,</hi> they must not think of catching <hi>things of Substance.</hi> And they who are intent upon the <hi>Manner</hi> only, must let slip the <hi>Matter.</hi> Not that all these Qualifications are not very desirable and advantageous both to Prophet and to People too; and that the One may wish for, and the Other labour to attain these good Accomplishments, to the better carrying on the Work, and the greater Edification; but that there is Danger of laying too much Stress upon these
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61463:5"/> Matters: The People find themselves mov'd and affected for the present, and are thereby tempted to regard no farther Edification, or to think they have already edified sufficiently, mistaking oft, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of their Fancies, for Operations on their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and their Understandings; and the Prophet is thereby in Danger to be tempted to proceed in Ways so easy and so acceptable, if he have not a good Share of Grace, and Honesty, and Prudence.</p>
            <p>It cannot well indeed be otherwise, but that Men who come with a light and trifling Spirit, prepared, and, as it were, resolv'd to be pleas'd with nothing but external Garbs and Modes of speaking, should come to any Purpose, or return the wiser or the better, let the Prophet say what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e'er he can. It is in this case that Men seldom find any more than they seek for; and 'tis very natural to think that Men that only come to gratify their Curiosity, to hear some new things, some fine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Notions, and some fanciful Discourse, and to observe the Method and the Style and way of Preaching, should go away dissatisfied if they meet <hi>not</hi> with these things, and perfectly unedified if they do.</p>
            <p>Another Reason of the People's Non-Proficiency, may be, their having <hi>no Opinion,</hi> or conceit <hi>at all</hi> of the Prophet's Abilities; this is a worse Extream than the other; very discouraging of the Prophet, damp
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61463:5"/> his Spirits mightily, and checks the Vigour of his Thought, and causes him sometimes to slacken his Endeavours. But whatever Effect it has on him, it cannot possibly have any good One on the People. They are thereby predisposed to meet whatever shall be offered them, with neglect or supercilious Contempt. They have prejudg'd his Performances already, and all he says, seems but as idle talking. When once Men entertain a Prejudice against Men's Persons or Abilities, it is not easie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd, or to attend to what they shall deliver. Either they will not let themselves be perswaded that what is said, is true and reasonable; or Truth it self becomes unacceptable from them: Men hear, and see, and judge, by their Affections. When once we have debas'd a Man in our Opinion, his very Looks become unlovely, his Actions are ungraceful, and all his Wisdom seems as Foolishness; the Spirit of Contradiction seizes on us, and we are ready to do Violence to our <hi>own</hi> Reason, rather than allow of <hi>his.</hi> This Complaint is of long stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, most Men mind more <hi>who it is that</hi> speaks that <hi>what it is</hi> that's spoken. So that since 'tis plain, Affections difference People's Persons, 'tis also plain they byass and corrupt Men's Judgments; and as the Excess corrupts them in their Favour, so want of Love corrupts them to their Prejudice. But, as I said, this is the worse Extream of the two,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61463:6"/> for a good Opinion will improve the meanest Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, some way or other, to its own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, whereas a bad one will not edifie under the ablest Ministry. So true it is, that light and idle People, bring the Satisfaction along with them which they think they come to seek for in these Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. They come, they think, to be pleas'd, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, they are pleas'd before with Fame, or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, and therefore come. One may say on this, as St. <hi>James</hi> says, on another Occasion, <hi>My Brethren, these things ought not to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Third Occasion of Peoples Non-Proficiency may be, Their having by their Choice, or Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or Education, taken up some odd Opinions and peculiar Fancies in Religion, contrary to what is commonly and authoritatively taught; and Men are frequently so fond of their own Conceits and private Notions, that they do not only entertain with great Dislike the Doctrines that oppose them, and the Reasons that confute them, but for <hi>their</hi> Sakes, they frequently reject and cast by all <hi>besides;</hi> they will not abide what they have nothing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, for the Sake of something that dislikes them; that is, a Man must be of my side altogether, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can talk acceptably, and if he do not agree with me in this or that particular, then I will dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent from him in any other; which shews more Love to our <hi>selves</hi> than <hi>Truth,</hi> and that we rather like to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61463:6"/> be <hi>humour'd</hi> than <hi>convinc'd.</hi> This is a very weak Occasion of Non-Proficiency, but as weak as it is it is too common; and besides I am assigning Reasons for such Effects as few or no Causes are sufficient for.</p>
            <p>No, not even that which I am next in the <hi>Fourth</hi> place to assing, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> The evil Life and vicious Practice of the Prophets; for though the wicked Conversation of the Priest, be the most horrible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach imaginable, and ministers occasion to the greatest Scandal possible, and shall be punish'd with the most intense Degree of Torment, yet it will by no means justifie any Imitation of his evil Practice, or excuse the Neglect or Contempt of his Doctrines that are agreeable to Reason, and confirm'd by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Because it is certain, all Men are oblig'd to live by <hi>Rule</hi> and not <hi>Example.</hi> And though the Priest be indispensibly obliged by all the Ties of Reason and Religion, to be himself the Example of the Rules of good Living, yet <hi>his</hi> Apostacy will cover no ones else from Blame or Punishment. Whether Priests the more immediate Ministers in God's Service, are not tied to greater Sanctity and Strictness of Life, than other People, by God's Laws, may furnish Matter for Dispute, because the Laws of Vertue and the Precepts of Morality are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and common to all Mankind together with the Priests, and all Men are obliged to be as good as possibly they can, and the Priests can be no more.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61463:7"/> But rather than contest this Matter now, I shall take it for granted, That Priests have a closer Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to live well and vertuously than other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that Vice as ill becomes <hi>them,</hi> as Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law does a Judge, though all Men are alike oblig'd to Justice and Impartiality; or as want of Honour and Respect to a Prince becomes a Courtier, though all Men are alike oblig'd to pay them all they can, and all that's due, and neither Judge nor Courtier can do more. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this their closer Obligation, to live holily and well than other Peoples, <hi>their</hi> Relaxation of the Reins of Discipline and living in the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and Defiance to their Doctrines, as they cannot encourage any else to follow them in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, so they ought not to prejudice the Truth or Vertue of those Doctrines, or to hinder the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them to the Amendment of Men's Lives. They do indeed too commonly and too easily do it, but 'tis with no Reason; there is no tolerably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring from one Man's evil Practice, to anothers evil Practice, and much less his Unbelief; there is no concluding the People's Security from the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or the Self-Condemnation of the Priest.</p>
            <p>The Scandal that is given by wicked Ministers, shall heat their Furnace Seven times hotter than the rest, but the Scandal <hi>taken</hi> shall not lessen any ones degree of Punishment; whoever offends by Example,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61463:7"/> shall be as guilty, and liable to as great an Infliction as the Crime it self deserves, and should have had, had there been no Example given, supposing that there be a Rule to walk by. <hi>For it is Rule we are to live, and shall be judg'd by, and not Example.</hi> An Example is indeed of use, to shew us that the Rule is practicable, and to excite us to Imitation, but every one in Truth is bound to himself the Example of the Rule. <hi>It is impossible,</hi> our Saviour says, <hi>but that Offences should come, and wo to that Man by whom they come, it were better for him that a Milstone were hanged about his Neck and he thrown into the Sea.</hi> This will unquestionably be the Fate of evil Pastors, that by vicious and disorderly living give occasion of Offence and falling to weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, but the falling thus and being thus offended is not hereby lessened or excus'd; their Misfortunes do not grow the lighter. As the One should not <hi>give,</hi> and shall be punished for <hi>giving,</hi> so the other should not <hi>take,</hi> and shall be punished For <hi>taking,</hi> that Offence, against a plain Rule and positive Command to the contrary.</p>
            <p>In very dubious and uncertain Matters, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may be as reasonable and justifiable a Byass as any else whatever, if it be of One that is of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd Integrity and Understanding, because the following such Example is following the best Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son we have, and acting according to the best of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61463:8"/> our Understanding, which is in dubious matters, or such as lie beyond our Reach, chusing the best for our selves we can. But in matters of Morality and plain Practice, where every ones Understanding is his Rule, and a sufficient one too, there, not an Hundred nor a Thousand Instances, are sufficient to acquit a Man (no not even to himself) offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against a known Rule; for it is not <hi>Number</hi> but <hi>Truth</hi> that we must follow. Methinks I need not argue much in this Behalf, to shew that People should not follow the Steps of wicked Prophets, whose Example they do commonly (and truly most deservedly) despise and hate; but the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Excuse that People make that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not profit under an evil Ministry, will do more than justifie what has been said on this Account. But it is, indeed, too near to flattering of our selves, to seek for Causes at such Distance, which lurk at home so near us, even in our Hearts. And though the Parable of the Sower of Seed were primarily intended by our Saviour to shew the Impediments, that would obstruct the Propagation of the Gospel at its first preaching; yet it is very proper and well fitted to express the several Causes that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct its Influence on the minds of Men, in its progression, even in every after Age and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And to some Enquirers of the Non-profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of Hearers under the Ministry, we may as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign this Fifth Cause.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:61463:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly,</hi> Some are Hearers <hi>by the way side, where the Word is sown, but when they have heard, Satan cometh immediately, and taketh away the Word that was sown in their Hearts.</hi> Some hear by <hi>Chance,</hi> and 'tis more than so, that they edify not at all with it. They stroll about like Vagrants, and light upon the Word of God, as on a thing they thought not of, and part with it as easily. They come without Design, without any Consideration, or Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Heart; and as the Sower cannot scatter with so even a Hand, but some will fall by the way Side, besides the Furrows and prepared Ground; so the Voice and Words of the Prophet will reach some that are as ill prepared to hear it, and who make so short and little use of it, that they can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly say they <hi>lost</hi> it. It is no difficulty for Satan to snatch that away, they found at unawares, and cared so little for, and held so weakly and so slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. 'Tis true indeed, that these unthinking Strag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are sometimes caught by something accidentally delivered to them, and from a wavering and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Faith, and loose Morals, are suddenly reclaim'd and fix'd, both in their Judgment, and a steady Course of Vertue and Obedience, but this is such an extraordinary unusual Operation of the Spirit of God upon the mind, that as there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of it made to any one, so there ought to be no Expectation of it. The least that any one can
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61463:9"/> bring towards his Edification, is an Intention and Desire of being edified; No one in Reason can expect to be so benefited against, or without their Will and Inclination. But neither is a previous bare Intention only to be edified sufficient, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny come with this, and yet return as empty as they came: It is also necessary that some after-Care suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, <hi>for Satan</hi> like a Bird of prey <hi>commeth immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and takes away the Seed,</hi> scarce cover'd over, <hi>that was sown in their Hearts;</hi> diverts them present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and will not suffer them to meditate or think deliberately on what they heard. He hates Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in the Sons of Men, and knows it is his mortal Enemy, and in a little time would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw his Kingdom, and therefore uses all his art and cunning to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Another sort there are, our Saviour tell us, of Auditors that are represented by the Seed falling on the stony Ground; <hi>Those hear the Word, and anon with Joy receive it, but having no Root, endure but for a time, for when Persecution or Affliction ariseth because of the Word, they are presently offended.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of People come to Church with very good Designs and Purposes, and behave themselves well and devoutly there, listen attentively, and are very much affected with what they hear, and stedfastly purpose to put in Practice what they find so appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to, and what concerns themselves. But when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61463:9"/> they come to make the Experiment, and put their good Resolves in Execution; the hold that Ease and Pleasure have taken on them is not easily let go; the Difficulties and Severities of Virtue and Religion stare them in the Face, and appear so formidable and unacceptable to humane Nature, that they immediately give up their better Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and fall again into their usual Courses. They hear with Joy, and receive with Joy, and apply with Joy, and resolve with Joy to profit themselves of what they hear, but the Afflictions of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Obedience, of Mortification, and the want of what they have so long been us'd to; the Persecution of Delight and Pleasure that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally persue and haunt the Mind; in a word, the leaving off delightful things, and taking up unusual and unacceptable Ones, is a great Cause of Non-Proficiency; the Doctrine is agreeable to Reason; they see its great Convenience and Necessity indeed, but the Difficulty of the Practice, spoils all, and sets them back again, and leaves them as their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions found them; they would be admirable Christians, if nothing but Consent of Reason and Judgment were wanting; if they might live as they desire and do, without forsaking what they like, and taking up with what they like by no means: if believing what we say and firmly purposing to act accordingly, were to edify, they would edify
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61463:10"/> most abundantly; but as to practising what they hear, they say with <hi>Naaman. The Lord pardon them in that thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another sort of unprofiting Hearers, are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented by our Saviour by the Seed that fell among the Thorns—<hi>Such as hear the Word, And the Cares of this World, and the Deceitfulness of Riches, and the Lusts of other things entring in choke the Word, and it becometh unfruitful.</hi> The former would have profited but for Pleasure, these would be edified but that Gain and Business hinder them. They hear right, and understand and apply right, but their minds are estrang'd and carried off, by their intense Desires of growing Rich, and by the Multiplicity of their Concerns, and clutter of Affairs. The World has taken such hold and fastening on their Hearts, that when they find themselves mov'd by any thing we say, and are inclin'd to loosen and relax, to mind their better and more lasting Interest, it still throws out some bait or other to detain and keep them, some weighty thing or other interferes, and either voids their Resolutions quite, or else deferrs them to a more convenient Season, which gives another like-Temptation Means and Opportunity to enter, and obtain its day of hearing, and so the Life is lost in a Circle of Resolutions and Defeats, in Promises and stedsast Purposes, and cold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints for want of Opportunities. As the Prophet
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61463:10"/> accuses in the Text: <hi>With their Mouth they shew much Love, but their Heart goeth after their Covetousness.</hi> They are sensibly affected with what they hear and learn, and like it very well, and express their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in Desires and Resolutions to observe and practise it, but their Hearts, when they come to Tryal, fail them and deceive them, and can't be disentangled from their Business and the Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their gainful Callings, and Designs. When their Minds aspire to heavenly things, this fatal Poise and Tendency to worldly Wealth, cloggs them and drags them downwards still, although a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Reason and Resolutions; and if this Son's Preferment and that Daughter's Fortune were secured, they could attend on God without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction; they would then forsake a vain and sinful World, and its deceitful Riches, and lay up better and more lasting Treasures in a better place, <hi>where neither Moth nor Rust doth corrupt, and where no Thieves break through and steal;</hi> but before this comes to pass, the Man grows old, and sees his little Images in Children's Children, and Nature quickens him again to greater Fondness, and they must have their Portions from new Toils and new Anxieties, and the Cares of this World begin again, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulness of Riches choaks the Word that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th so oft been heard with Joy and Gladness, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all his Approbation and his Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61463:11"/> to improve, yet it becomes unfruitful.</p>
            <p>I know not well, how proper you may think it to assign such Causes of Men's Non-proficiency un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Ministry of Preaching, when the Pretence and End of Preaching is to remove those Causes and Impediments: It looks as if Physicians should excuse their ill Success, by assigning such and such Obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the Energy of their Medicines, when 'tis the proper Busines<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Art and Calling to remove those very Obstructions; it may rather seem to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the Weakness of the Word of the Lord, to say that the Lusts and Pleasures, the Cares and Love of Riches hinder it from being fruitful, when 'tis that Word it self, that is to mortify those Lusts, subdue those Longings, remove those Cares, and kill that Love of Riches at the very Root. To this we must say, that however powerfully and strongly the Spirit of God may sometimes operate on the Souls of Men, work off their Hearts, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations from the Riches or the Pleasures of this Life, and change them unaccountably and almost in an Instant, which no one can deny has sometimes, in somes Cases, happened; yet this is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and no where promis'd, and therefore no where to be look'd for, or depended on; it is like mighty, unexpected, undeserved Favours to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with all Joy and Thankfulness, and to be carefully improved to all Advantage, but 'tis what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61463:11"/> no one else must look for, though in the same Condition, and the same Necessity. The ordinary and usual Way, is arguing and enforcing People's Duties, by their proper Motives; shewing the Reasonableness, Convenience and Necessity of their performing them, which must for its Effect depend upon the Grace of God, and on the Will, Capacity, and Teachableness of the Hearer. So that in the ordinary Conversion of a Sinner from the Evil of his Ways, these three are unavoidably concern'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The Minister must do his Part, which is to shew the Unreasonableness of the Ways of Sin, the natural Turpitude and unagreeable Deformity there is in Vice, how opposite it is to the Natural Light within, and to the Dictates of our Conscience, how prejudicial to them as they are Men, and live in this World, with Respect to bodily Health, to Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and a good Name, and to their thriving in their Callings. Next to the Reasonableness of Virtue and Obedience, he can only shew the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience and Necessity of complying with the Will of God; the Peace and Pleasure and Content of Mind that constantly attends the doing it, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ineffable, eternal Recompence that follows it, hereafter. Or on the other Hand, the Pain, uneasyness, and terrible Anxiety of Heart, the Affliction of a fearful and suspicious Mind, the Reproaches of Reason, the Remorse of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61463:12"/> and that Hell on Earth that constantly attends the guilty and the obstinately disobedient, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a fearful looking for of Judgment, that will certainly consign them over to Pains and Sorrows that will know no Measure nor no end. This is all the Minister can do, to urge Men to their Duties by their Fitness, by promises and threats, and by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other Motives are contain'd in holy Scriptures, to press them in, and out of Season, and to contribute all he can, to their producing their Effect. And though there may be mighty difference in the Way and Manner of proposing things, that some Men do it much more forcibly, and clearly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly, than others, and in a much more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Way, yet even the best of them can do no more than just propose, and lay these things before them; <hi>Paul may plant and Apollos water, but 'tis from God that the increase must come;</hi> there is both need of his preventing and assisting Grace, and 'tis from him we must expect the Blessing. 'Tis certain that without him of our selves we can do nothing, but it is as certain that he never fails what Grace is necessary and sufficient for that purpose, if Men will use their best Endeavours, and employ his gifts as he shall order and direct them. Where-ever any thing depends, for its Effect, on God and Man, in Conjunction, and Co-operation together, we may be sure that God is never wanting to perform
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61463:12"/> his part, if Man will do but his; and though it may be difficult (in many Cases utterly impossible) for any one to know, or to describe the Methods and the Measures of God's Grace, in working on the Hearts and Minds of People, to Conversion, yet of this we may be sure, That Work it does, unless we our selves put some Hindrance and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment in its Way; and of this we may be also full as sure, That the Operations of his Grace, and holy Spirit, do not at all depend upon our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or our Understanding how and when they operate: And that therefore, there is no expecting or attending till it operate, that we may our selves begin; for Grace, like the Kingdom of God, comes not by Observation; but we must do our Duty, all that possibly we can, our selves, and God will not be wanting. So that no one can excuse or cover his Continuance in Sin, upon Pretence that the Grace of God will not help him out; that, for his Part, he is very willing, and uses his utmost Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to extricate and disentangle himself, but that the Grace of God is wanting to him, without which he cannot stir: That's true, That without the Grace of God he cannot extricate himself, but it neither is nor can be true, that if he be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self willing, and uses his utmost Endeavours, that the Grace of God will fail, for it is by God's Grace that he is willing, and by God's Grace that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61463:13"/> thus to free himself; for naturally and of our selves we are told, we can neither <hi>will,</hi> nor <hi>do</hi> any thing of that Kind: and the applying all such Arguments and Motives to our Duty, as it hath pleased God to reveal to us, and the using all those Means and Instruments which he discovers to us, and designs for those good Purposes, is using and improving of the Grace of God, that Grace that is ordinarily requisite and necessary to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version. So that the Guilt at length will unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably devolve upon the Offender only. God cannot possibly be wanting, the Prophet cannot easily, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> so far as to excuse the Offender, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Men themselves are only chargeable, and they must look at home, for their Conversion, or their Condemnation: From all which it will appear, that though the Objection be so far true, that it is the Work of God's Word, and proper Business of the Preacher to cure these Evils, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move these Obstacles, and to subdue these Lusts and evil Appetites that hinder the Word of God from taking its Effect, and to reduce the disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and reclaim the wandring Sinner from his evil Ways, yet it is by no means true, that it is deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the Grace of God that it works not forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and irresistibly upon the Minds of Men to their Conversion; nor to the Power of God's Word in the Mouths and Sermons of his Messengers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61463:13"/> that their preaching and endeavours prove so ineffectual and unedifying; since all the force they either do or can use, is natural and moral Suasion; they can but stir the Passions and Affections, and work upon the Reason and Understanding of People by suitable and proper Arguments, and whether they shall do that, depends very much upon the People themselves, but whether, when that is done, it shall prove effectual, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> shall influence them to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, depends entirely on them. They can, but like Physicians, prescribe a true and proper Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, and tell the Dangers of continuing in that evil State, but still the Use and Application of this Remedy depends and will depend upon the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
            <p>It remains, That I make an Inference or Two from what hath been said, and so conclude. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Since it is plain from the constant, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and usual Method of God's proceeding in the converting and changing the People's minds, that they must, to make them blameable and punishable by him, be at Liberty, whether they will receive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction or no, and practise afterwards what they shall be convinced becomes their Duty; since it is plain, I say, they must be at their Liberty, it is also plain that the Fault must lie upon themselves, and that they have it in their power to mend; and since all the Causes that either have been, or that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61463:14"/> can be reasonably assigned for People's Nonprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency under the ordinary and standing Ministry of Praching, are such as do entirely depend upon the People themselves, there is no longer Time allowed for their Enquiries why, and their Complainings that they <hi>do not</hi> edifie and profit more: For now the Power is in their Hands, and such a Power, as may be for their Edification, or Destruction: Life and Death is set before them; the Bread of Life, the Word of God; that as they chuse, and use it, will be sure to prove either the Savour of Death to Death, or else the Word of Everlasting Life and Health: And therefore there is need of all their Care and Diligence in Hearing and Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Treasuring up, and Practising their Duties, that they may not come together for the worse, but better. As therefore every Body owns they come to Church with a Design to hear, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in, what they know not; or to be put in mind of what they knew, but had forgotten, and to be moved to practise it; so the least that they can do in common Kindness to themselves, is, to see they do not lose their Labour: But when it is moreover a Business of the Greatest Moment and Importance in the World they are about, they are obliged undoubtedly to hear to purpose, and, to that End, to come with Minds prepared to hear the Truth, and to receive it kindly, though it thwart their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61463:14"/> nearest Interests, or their dearest Inclinations; to lay aside all Prejudice and Prepossession, either against Men's Persons, or their Doctrines, and to attend alone to what is said, and weigh its Reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableness with Candour and Impartiality, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Truth, and its Conformity with Holy Scriptures. Men must not judge of either Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, or their Doctrines, by their own Affections or Desires: They must not do as <hi>Ahab</hi> did by <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah; I know,</hi> saith he, <hi>there is one Micaiah, the Son of Imlah, by whom we may enquire of the Lord; but I hate him, for he doth not prophesie Good concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning me, but Evil.</hi> The weak Prince had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Truth at all, but had rather be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, than not pleased; and hated him, because he prophesied unacceptable Things. Men must not look to be indulged in Things unlawful, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God; or that his Message should not be delivered openly and plainly, though it would wound their Ears, and pierce their Hearts with many Sorrows. He ill becomes his Character, and little understands the Nature or the Dignity of his Calling, that will for Interest or Ambition, Fear or Favour, Love or Hate, dissemble in these Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: And he is lamentably over-run with Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to himself, that would be for the present chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Peace, and false Security, and knows it cannot last, but that his Dream will quickly end,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61463:15"/> and he shall wake in lasting and substantial Misery.</p>
            <p>As it is the Prophet's Part to say with that <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah,</hi> (when he was tempted to delude the King with soft and pleasing Prophecies,) <hi>As the Lord liveth, what the Lord saith unto me, that will I speak;</hi> so is it to be the People's Part to answer as the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> did to <hi>Moses,</hi> when he had been telling all the Words and Judgments of the Lord, to say, <hi>All the Words which the Lord hath said, will we do, and be obedient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are not to consider whether what we say be acceptable to Flesh and Blood; whether the Doctrines we deliver be consistent with your Profit, or your Pleasure; whether they cross your Interest, or your Inclination, nor any thing besides; but whether God hath spoken by us, whether the Things we say be so, or no, in Holy Scriptures; whether the Duties we exhort to be so much your Interest and Concern to follow and perform, as we persuade; whether such Peace and Satisfaction here, and such Eternal, excellent Rewards hereafter, are assigned and promised to your Faith, and your Obedience; and whether such amazing Punishments and Pains in Everlasting Fire are treasured up against the Day of Wrath and Retribution, for the ungodly Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and impenitent. And if you find these Things are so, you will make the Inference with St. <hi>Peter; What manner of Persons ought you to be in all holy</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61463:15"/>
               <hi>Conversation and Godliness?</hi> And see the great Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity there is of complying with St. <hi>James</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>To lay a-part all Filthiness, and Superfluity of Naughtiness, and receive with Meekness the engraffed Word, which is able to save your Souls. To be Doers of the Word, and not Hearers only, deceiving your own Selves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If it was thus even with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and the other Messengers of God, with <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, with Christ himself and his Disciples; if they had Reason to complain of their unkind Reception in the World, of the Hardness of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Hearts and Unbelief, and of the little Fruit they found of all their Care and Labour in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their Offices; if Men were deaf to all their Charms, charmed they never so wisely, warmly and affectionately, there is less need that any now-adays, the faint and feeble Imitators of their Zeal and Vertue, should complain of their hard Fortune upon these Occasions. It is, in truth, a very great Discouragement in it self, to see such ardent Longings after People's Benefit, such zealous Prosecutions of it, in such painful and industrious manner, prove so ineffectual as they oft-times do. But though it may be Matter of Complaint and Sorrow, yet it is none of Fear, or of Repentance, when they do their Duty: They have these great Examples set before them, as well
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61463:16"/> for their Comfort, as their Imitation, that they should follow them in the careful and Conscientious Discharge of their great Office, and leave, with them, the Issue in the Hands of God; well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that whatever be the Event, they shall be judg'd with righteous Judgment, and shall receive a glorious Recompence at God's Hand, for all their good Designs, and good Endeavours, although the Folly, or the Obstinacy of ungodly People may have frustrated them both.</p>
            <p>The Labours of the Prophets have a Three Fold End—The First, and best, and most design'd by God, is the effecting his good Purposes in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People to Repentance and Salvation; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is the discharging of their Duties, and the exemplifying their Obedience in the several Instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Commands, and the saving of their own Souls. The Third and last, and the most lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table one, is, the justifying God in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and vindicating him in his Inflictions; that all Pretence of Ignorance, and Inability, and of Forgetfulness, may be destroyed by their Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Admonitions and Reproofs, and by their frequently repeated Cries and Calls, both in and out of Season, to Repentance, that Men may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Condemnation in their Bosoms to the Day of Doom, and acquit their Judge before the World of Men and Angels. <hi>That they</hi> (as St. <hi>Austin</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:61463:16"/> somewhere says, with which I will conclude) <hi>who will not glorify God's Mercy in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Lives here, may glorify his Justice in their Punishment hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 8. line the last, for <hi>damp</hi> read <hi>damps.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:61463:17"/>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Queen, at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> on <hi>February</hi> the 12th. 169.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, at St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> the 11th. of <hi>April,</hi> 1692. Being the Fast-Day.</p>
            <p>Another Sermon Preached at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi>-Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>December</hi> the 11th, 1692. before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and Court of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen.</p>
            <p>All Three by <hi>W. Fleetwood,</hi> Chaplain in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to Their Majesties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Sold by</hi> Thomas Newborough, <hi>at the</hi> Golden-Ball <hi>in St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s</hi> Church-Yard.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61463:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>